<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Huls pillar of providence erected: or The providentiall columne, setting out heavens care for deliverance of that people, with extraordinary power and providence from the bloud-sucking Cavaliers, who had for six weeks closely besieged them. By T. C. minister of Gods Word. Imprimatur Charles Herle.</title>
            <author>Coleman, Thomas, 1598-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E37_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859350</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E37[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Huls pillar of providence erected: or The providentiall columne, setting out heavens care for deliverance of that people, with extraordinary power and providence from the bloud-sucking Cavaliers, who had for six weeks closely besieged them. By T. C. minister of Gods Word. Imprimatur Charles Herle.</title>
                  <author>Coleman, Thomas, 1598-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Rounthwait,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Coleman by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 19th 1643"; the second 4 in 1644 is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hull (England) --  History --  Siege, 1644 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HVLS PILLAR OF Providence erected: OR The Providentiall Columne, ſetting out Heavens care for Deliverance of that people, with extraordinary Power and Providence from the bloud-ſucking Cavaliers, who had for ſix weeks cloſely beſieged them.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. C.</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 26.1.</bibl>
               <p>In that day ſhall this Song be ſung in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> we have aſtrong Citie, Salvation ſhall God appoint for wals and bulwarks.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ZECH. 3.2.</bibl>
               <p>Is not this a brand pluck'd out of the fire.</p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CHARLES HERLE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Rounthwait,</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111424:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t where are the nine</hi> (ſaith Chriſt.) The Lord longs much to ſee us after he hath freed us; in our diſtreſſe we long for deliverance, and being delivered he longs for acknowledgement. <hi>Deborah</hi> after her victorie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened her ſelfe with ſo loud an inſtigation, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to awaken others, That ſhe might not returne with the leprous <hi>Samaritan</hi> alone in her acknowledgment. Thus this holy-man, Gods faithfull Miniſter, and our deare brother, an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the great and wonderfull worke done by our God for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagured Towne, the deliverance, a mercy he had a ſhare in, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and our ſelves: It was the place of refuge to many perſecuted and plundered Families, and to ours and his; here were met in one from the two ſpoiled Counties of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lincolne,</hi> of all ſorts a great multitude. Here we comfortably enjoyed our peace; here publikely and privately we jointly ſought it's peace, of the fruit whereof it is now a partaker from the God of peace. And therfore in all places and ages, that it may be ſaid for <hi>Hull,</hi> what God hath done, as we can do no more, ſo no leſſe then clap our hands, and being of the number of the Lords redeemed ones, cry out and ſay, <hi>God hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad:</hi> And O let all places be filled with the ſame glorie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Tho: Micclethwait.</item>
                     <item>Philip Nye.</item>
                     <item>Th: Coleman.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111424:2"/>
            <head>To the Lords diſperſed and ſcattered ones, beloved of the Father in the Sonne, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together from divers Quarters and Countries into <hi>Hull,</hi> the Neſt of Gods providence, Grace Divine, and greeting Chriſtian.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O you beloved the faire and strong hand of heaven hath bin fully manifeſted, at first plucking you as a brand out of the fire of the enemies fury, that watched for you where you li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and now again the ſame hand of heaven hath viſited you with new favour, putting the proud adverſarie by, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his combe, when he was ready to chop you for the pot, in the place where you ſojourned. Remember now <hi>Salomons</hi> Scripture, <hi>The Lord was angry with him, becauſe his heart was turned from the Lord God of Iſrael, which had appeared unto him twice.</hi> He has twice appeared marvellous in mercie to you, and look'd upon you as no stranger in the place where you were ſtrangers. Remember the day, wherin theſe thoughts tooke you up continually, what ſhall we doe, whither ſhall we goe, what way ſhall we flie, what courſe ſhall we take, that may be pleaſing to God, ſafe for us. And now let me tell you whither you ſhall flie, even unto the Lord with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts who hath ſo wonderfully magnified his favour towards you. I have ſeene a failing in the Towne hitherto, as ſecure as if never in danger, as proud as if no matter of humbling, as prophane as if great deliverances did not bring great engagements to holineſſe, as unthankefull, as if not beholding to God, as ſuperſtitious, as if the maſter of Ceremonies, and not the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies had ſaved them. But doe not you faile too, let the Towne be beholding to you for your prayers and your praiſes, be you their Maſons to helpe to make up the breaches of their walls, their country husbands to amend their hedges, and make up gappes where Gods wrath might breake-in. The Lord give you patient hearts in theſe oppreſſing times and hard charges, and abundance of thankfulneſſe to <hi>Jehovah Niſſi</hi> the Lord your Banner, that both you and the Church of God may be cloathed with the garments of ſalvation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111424:3"/>
            <head>Divinae Providentiae Sacrum,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Indian Hand had ſome reaſon it ſeemes, which put upon it that name of the <hi>Ile of Providence,</hi> the ſpeciall hand of heaven ruling and leading the ſearching ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers to this place; and bringing them through long labours and hard indeavours to pitch and plant on that ground. And before I have done with this narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and diſcourſe; I ſhall make it good, that there is ground for the naming of this <hi>Kingſton</hi> or <hi>Hull, A Town of Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where, as on a Stage of Mercy, Divine Providence has of late act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed parts of love, care, power, kindneſſe gloriouſly, before, and for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie both Spectators and receivers: The Lord hath ſo done his marvellous workes, that they ought to bee had in remembrance of all them that feare him.</p>
            <p>If any be ſuch a ſtranger in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as has not heard nor knowne the things, that are come to paſſe in theſe dayes, I will informe him, (to quicken my ſelfe, and others to gratefullneſſe,) how the Lord has heated the furnace of his love, and care for <hi>Hull,</hi> ſeven times hotter then he has done for any towne in <hi>England.</hi> And gladly would I have the Land to take notice of it, becauſe though the Sun riſe in one corner of the Heavens the Eaſt; yet the light, heat and influence of the Sun fills the whole Earth, and cheriſhes every creature. So, though the beſt part of the Kernell of this deliverance falls particularly into <hi>Hulls</hi> mouth, and the people there, both in-dwellers and the Lords ſojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yet doubtles it ſends much good influence, &amp; reviving beams into the Goſpells cauſe, now quarrelled for, into the Church, into this Kingdome, into the Parliament, into the armies on foote, for the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing of our Realme, from the pawes of the Lyon, and the beare: the Churches Lyon, that would oppreſſe it with <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> and popiſh prelacy, and the Common wealths ſavage Beare, that would devoure Truth, juſtice and righteouſneſſe, and leave neither law, nor liberty nor rights, for the Subject, but what muſt come out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of licentious Atheiſme, where will and power ſhall create Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy and the acts of it. Now that the Lord hath baniſhed ſuch blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111424:3"/>and cruell Gaolers, which laid upon all that came under their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, iron yoakes and fetters, how can we doe leſſe then ſeeke out the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this deliverance, and give him the cordiall and reall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements of thankefull ſpirits, which either ſpeaking, writing or printing may make knowne to our little world of <hi>England,</hi> leaſt the glory of God, which, of all other things ſhould never know a funerall, and be buried in oblivion, be any way obſcured or ecclipſed. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we enquire after the father, and mother, and nurſe of this amiable and comfortable child of ſalvation, which we can never looke in the face, but it makes us ſmile with joy: we can finde none to owne it, but only Providence divine, which has done all. This hath been ſo clearly and manifeſtly ſtirring, from the <hi>Alpha</hi> to the <hi>Omega</hi> of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that we ſilence all ſubſervient Miniſters, and miniſtred helpes, as ſtrength, guns, ſwords, munition, care and induſtrie, and onely write God with great letters and figures, and make all other great helpes, to be but as a great cipher without divine concurrence. When we name Providence, as the ſuperintendent and ſuperefficient of all, we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not chance or fortune, the Ethnickes providence, nor that of the Stoickes, who made providence a fortune or fate-telling old-woman, to adminiſter all things, as the univerſall ſoule of the world. But by it we underſtand the ſpeciall care, and love of God towards his, which is at great coſt, and charges of infinite power, fore-ſight and wiſdome, to worke in all and every individuall thing for his people,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lilius. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald. de dijs Gent. Syntag.</hi> 76.</note> and having wrought it, to make it again be directed to worke for their good. And if at <hi>Delos</hi> the blind Heathens for ſome conceived bleſſing could erect a Temple and call it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Temple of Providence:</hi> Doe not Chriſtians owe as much to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as they to their <hi>Jove?</hi> Shall not our <hi>Delos,</hi> our <hi>Hull</hi> be called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Temple of Providence,</hi> where it hath been moſt admirably conſpicuous, and efficacious for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance. It is well knowne,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> how heavenly care did at firſt reſerve this Towne;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that at firſt it fell not under the unruly rule of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Royaliſts, who never thinke they doe any thing royally,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but when they make <hi>Rome</hi> bluſh,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> with being more ſuperſtitious and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous then ſhe is: or when they make beaſts bluſh, with being more ſavage and cruell then they: or make <hi>Pagans</hi> and Heathens bluſh, in being more unjuſt and unhoneſt then they: or make the devill and bell bluſh, to ſee them more zealous and deepe blaſphemers, then they. In theſe actions all their royalty and cavaleriſme conſiſt. What a ſpeciall hand of heaven was that, prevented this Marqueſſe (whom blood not in his owne veines, but bloud plenteouſly ſhed out of all the veines of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111424:4"/>the North, hath raiſed to this title of <hi>Marqueſſe</hi>) from being governor of it at firſt, when his Majeſtie ſent him and offered him for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the Towne. The prevention of ſuch a Hornet, that he was not ſet over his Bee-hive, deſerves our tongues to ſpeake as loud as the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian Magitians,</hi> and to ſay, this was <hi>Digitus Dei,</hi> the finger of God. For ſay he had bin the reſident ruler here; what an influence of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief would he have ſent hence againſt <hi>London,</hi> Parliament, and all the places under the rule of well ordered juſtice and peace? How would this have been the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſcumme-pot, into which would have been gathered all the living and working villanie or Atheiſme of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk, France, Holland, Flanders,</hi> &amp;c. And what Country ſoever would have ſent men-beaſts, that in a mercenary ſouldiarie are willing, to ſell their ſoules in any warre, yea will take the pay of hell, to fight againſt heaven? But bleſſed be the eye of heaven, that watcht, and the hand of heaven that wrought another way, and brought this key of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to hang at the Parliaments girdle, that they ſhould not be in an hourely feare of this, as of a Northerne <hi>Algiers,</hi> or neſt of Sea and land Pirates. Why is <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> and not <hi>Hull</hi> in their power, a continuall vexation to the good cauſe? There is no reaſon of it, but what lies in Gods breaſt and boſome, ſo he liked, ſo he would have it.</p>
            <p>Under Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> the Lord began to put this Towne, as a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ring on his finger. How did the Lord animate the Governour and his ſmall forces to ſtand unappaled before his Majeſtie, when he comes in his owne perſon, and with all his power he could then make, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, nay to command the rendring of the Towne into his power, yet even then God made wormes ſtronger then the Lion, when <hi>Hotham</hi> royally ſtood and feared neither Herald, nor Proclamation, nor the voyce of a provoked King, which is the meſſenger of death O that this fine gold had never changed! But O the miſery of fooliſh man, made drunke with authority and power! <hi>Hotham</hi> honoured like a King, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as an Emperour; ſitting in peace, that might have had the Country for the good cauſe wait on his whiſtle; how has he degenerated and ſoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all his fair burning light, in ending with a ducking down of the ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, breathing at laſt with a vaporous, &amp; ill ſavoured exit. Time will try, and juſtice will boult out (I fore-judge not, nor anticipate our Iudges of this cauſe.) Whether juſtly father or ſon <hi>Hotham,</hi> or both, be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of miſcarriages in the North, at <hi>Yorke,</hi> of the Queens entrance u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, of <hi>Scarboroughs</hi> and <hi>Chomeleyes</hi> baſe Apoſtaſie, of the Weſt crying out of the riſing Sun, and ſaying, all her miſerie came from the Eaſt, where Egyptian reeds did not only faile them, but pierce them,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111424:4"/>and helpe them to be covered in that Chaos of tyranny, wherein that good and goodly Country now lies low and poor, only rich (beſides Gods ſecret favour) in fulneſſe of oppreſſions and cruelty. I leave theſe ſervants to the judgement of their maſter, who will make their ſins appeare as mid-night, or their righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as mid-day in due time: I know it is indeed thought and ſaid, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Hotham</hi> and <hi>Cholmley,</hi> that <hi>Scorborough</hi> and <hi>Scarborough</hi> are the ſprings of moſt of our miſery in the North. Let others ſay as they pleaſe, Gods candle in fit ſeaſon will ſeeke out darkeſt corners. Let the juſt have his righteouſneſſe for cloathing, and let the unjuſt be arrayed with his own confuſion, and ſhame as with a cloake. Proceed we to the change of Governours and ſee miracles, and great peeces of extraordinary providence in that. In one mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning gates, walles, block-houſes, armes, men, commanders, guns, ſhips, all that is called ſtrong, is eaſily and quickly yeelded to the power of the Towne, no bloud-ſhed, no ſoule lies gaſping, no ſtreets know ſtreames of bloud, but wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for all this, why, this is wonderfull, friends, kindred, deare ones, in places of truſt, yet none reſiſting, but yeelding up office and power, as being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with power and reaſon for it, or both. So great a thing, ſo long and ſtrongly ſetled, ſo eaſily altered and turn'd without combuſtion &amp; broil, would make an Atheiſt, that ſaw it, name God and Providence, for that very actions ſake. Beſides, the enraged Towne, againſt their ſuſpected Governour, being ſo calmed into juſtice, and prudently reſerving father and ſon, to be weighed by the Parliaments ballance, and not precipitately cutting out for themſelves, was a ſpeciall favour of God, to honour them with ſo well a carried buſineſſe. Then loe again the Artifice, and rare working of Architectonicall providence; verily thou art a God that hideſt thy ſelfe O God of Iſrael the Saviour. At this preſent, things are thus carried at <hi>Hull,</hi> the noble <hi>Fairfax</hi> is in his Weſtern de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and <hi>Beverly</hi> is ready to be chopt for the pot, by the aſſaulting enemy. Marke how the wheele runs. From <hi>Beverly</hi> the enemy is repulſed with ſhame and loſſe. But in the Weſt, two or three dayes after, the ſwarmes of New Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles waſpes ſting the Armie of the honoured <hi>Fairfax,</hi> there he and his heroick Sonne, after faire hopes looſe the day, quit the field (though to the great coſt of the adverſary) and leave that nobleſt part of the Country in the hands of the ignobleſt men (if inhumanity be ignobility) where as they were bred and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled, ſo they maintain it, there is no good play unleſſe ſome play the devill in it. How have they imitated that infernall paternity of theirs, by being as cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell and unmercifull to that worthy people, as hell could make them. Then tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough what dangerous pathes and parts of Countries did the Lord bring hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and his ſon, and the remainders of his ſcattered Army? How did the Lord hard before this fore defeat, make Hull ready for them, whoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and longings waited for ſuch a Governour at the gates of heaven? Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111424:5"/>but the times of theſe things falling out, that Hul ſhould be made fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Governour, fit to ſuccour a diſperſed people, who fled from a bloudy ſword and ſpeare. Let Hull and Weſtern diſperſed ones, and the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome contend about it, which of them has the largeſt ſhare of fatherly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in this thing. O the providence is much for us, may Hull ſay, that we ſhould receive ſo faithfull and right a Governour in our neceſſity. It is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for us may Weſt ſay, that we ſhould get ſuccour there. It is providence for us, may the whole kingdom ſay, that ſo quickly the government was ſetled there, and though there was ſo great a wound, yet the Lord quickly prepared a good and great plaiſter. How deepe is the Lords wiſdom in his doings? How can hee ſtrangely, at one and the ſame time, win and loſe, cut and cure, wound and heale, throw downe and raiſe up his people, and make one and the ſame cloud both darke and lightſome?</p>
            <p>Let the people of God obſerve it, they never have any notable fall or affliction, but God gives them ſome notable riſe after it, to ſtand on high ground againe, and to meet with ſome comfort and bleſſing ſucceeding it, of ſuch a depth and latitude, as entered not into their imaginations. And now <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> railes and <hi>Thraſoes</hi> boaſt, and every <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, now opens his mouth, and laughs to ſee Chriſt lie loaden with a croſſe in the ſtreets of <hi>Leedes</hi> and <hi>Bradford.</hi> Now the Iriſh Prelate, the biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> muſt turne the Pſalmes of <hi>David</hi> into a ſcornfull Jigge, and muſt not only abuſe the Saints of God, but the Scripture of God. The Miniſters pulpit is his ſtage, which hath bin commonly the: May-pole where ſcorners of Gods Saints have danced themſelvs giddy, and there he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends he will ſtir them up to give thanks to God, and to God alone, in theſe words of <hi>David: I will not truſt in my bow, neither ſhall my Sword ſave me, but thou haſt ſaved us from our enemies,</hi> &amp;c. Pſ. 44.6, 7. But he forgetting his theame, ſo dotes on his Marqueſſe,
<note place="margin">Si perga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad acuta reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, plus toge lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſêre rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toricae. Tertull de pallio.</note> that he muſt needs make him the bow and the ſword, as though he by his care and wiſe carriage had freed now all York-ſhire from oppreſſion and from the cruſhing of the Parliaments friends, and now there was nothing but one poor corner of caitiffs, all ſedition and faction now laid gaſping within the wals of Hull. Let not Biſhops ſpeak of oppreſſion, for they have bin <hi>Pharaohs</hi> moſt curſt task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, ſet up to afflict the Iſrael of God. Nor let Yorke be the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall at this time, to judge the diſperſed of Chriſt, that are met in Hull. After that way, Sr Biſhop, which you call ſedition, there are ſuch Saints ſerve God, as the latchet of whoſe ſhooes (ſaving the reverence of your bicorned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) you are not worthy to looſe. Well ſedition and faction lies gaſping within the walls of Hull; what then? Why then New-caſtle and his Army muſt come hither to the funerall of it, if it lie gaſping, it will die ſhortly, and they will be ſo officious, as to come and cloſe our eyes, and carry us to our grave; or if we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111424:5"/>be not ſo neare death, they can think of ſuch a thing as this, Come let us kill them that the inheritance may be ours.</p>
            <p>About the 4th of September, that goodly Town of <hi>Beverley</hi> fals into the hands of a merciles adverſary; ours beholding their great numbers, and conſidering the ſtate of the Town to be ſuch, as it could not be held againſt them, though our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers had bin trebled. Wherupon warning is given to retire and leave it, and ſome no doubt were to blame, that left ſome leſſer peeces of Ordnance there, and did not timely convey them away, which they might have done. <hi>Beverley</hi> ſmarted then on all ſides by enemies cruelty, by friends negligence, preſently is the Town made bare and ſtript naked, and compelled to ſpeake largely of the little charity, &amp; mercy of the promoters of the Catholike cauſe, who are <hi>ſemperide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> inhumane &amp; barbarous. Hard before their coming, one <hi>Buſhell</hi> a kinſman of the infamous <hi>Buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> (who is filled with more then four pecks of an Iſcarioticall ſpirit) came with a Tinker, himſelfe acting a bad mettall man with him, to view both Beverleyes and Huls works, having done it, were at length taken priſoners, and found to be bad mettall. Having ſwallowed Beverley they make Hull ready for the dreſſer, and their curſed Cooks made a great fire, hoping this Town ſhould be their roaſt-meat. They begin their ſiege, and have all kind of furies redreſſed with ſnakes to torment us. With them are come, as goads in their ſides, to ſet them on, and as candles in the darke to guide them, the fox-heads, ſubtill, cunning, and buſie ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Hull, which ſhe had vomited out, whoſe names are in the booke of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of vipers, which have watring teeth to eat thorough their mothers bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. The poor arayed and forced ſouls are made to tugg and worke worſe then the ſlaves at Adrianople, day and night, to raiſe Mounts and Works with turves and baskets, to brew our ruine. It will not be amiſſe, to ſee how God works the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of his people with many croſſe thrids, and makes a ſmooth web in the end of that, which has many knots in the beginning. Wheras at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming we had a ſpring-tide that might have flown with ſtreams of moleſtation to them, and hindred their works, if ours could have agreed to cut the banks, and lend them ſome ſalt water, yet ſo it pleaſed God to divide the conſults and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of men about it, that this is hindred, and therby they exceedingly furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in hopes to warme themſelves at our fire. Nay, when afterward there were found Propoſitions, upon rationall grounds, of daming up the freſh water, ſo as it ſhould over-flow very much to the much annoying of them, it may be to loſſe of all their peeces, and for much comfort to us, out of Town for ground and cattell, for helping them within Towne with ſufficiency of freſh waters; yet it pleaſed the Lord to throw all theſe devices out. Divine providence bids this humane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſtand by and ſtep out of the way, that not <hi>Joab,</hi> but <hi>David</hi> might have the name of the day. Humane helpe and induſtrie is good, though oftentimes evil in the abuſe, when men make them vails and curtains to hide the divine face, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111424:6"/>we do not ſo much ſee and admire the beauty of it. God thus in one and the ſame buſines weds together our comfort and his glory, even by thoſe things that ſeem to forbid the banes. Ours had ſoon after the beginning of the ſiege, a ſallie out with a good number of men upon them in their quarters at Anlabie, they had ſome intelligence, though it was early in the morning, ours had ſome prevalence, and our ſouldiers ſome were too buſie fingring their carriages, and looking after pocketings, ſo as though we brought divers of theirs priſoners, and ſome of them were ſlain, yet we alſo had ſome of ours taken, that we might take our ſelves for our ſin, that muſt needs pick the Lords day morning for ſuch a work, as we being the aſſaulters, might have well found another day for it. Every night the enemy gets a freſh worke, and with new incroaches and approaches, comes nigher us, ſo that in the morning we ſtand wondring, to ſee what is done that night. In the ſpace of 6 weeks ſiege, they ſeem to have ſo beſtraitned us, as there is no hopes of deliverance; but that their hopes and ours are not alike. The Cater-pillars that follow the campe, are invited from York, and thoſe parts, to come, and carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the plunder of the rich and goodly Town of Hull.</p>
            <p>I ſhall diſpatch the particulars of Gods ſingular providence in the remaining part, to the happy upſhot of the buſines, by borrowing 15 branches of this ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I find them fitly ſummed upon a Sermon at the low-Church, on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne day of thankſgiving, and celebration of ſo rare a peece of providence in the fore-noon, <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. being the ſeven-night after, only putting in ſome additions of inlargement, as quickning colours to make the picture looke more lively. The text diſcourſed on, as the bellows to blow up the flame of praiſe was <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9. <hi>And it ſhall be ſaid in that day, loe this is our God, we have waited for him, and he will ſave us. This is the Lord, we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> In which, after many other things the Sermon proceeded to urge rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in Gods ſalvation after this manner. We ſhould not only ſpeake of Gods acts, but as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſaith, we ſhould wiſely conſider of Gods doings, and gather up <hi>ramenta auri,</hi> all the filings and little ſparks of gold, becauſe mercies are a ſingular and rare mettall.</p>
            <p>From the 120. Pſalm there are 15. Pſalms, which are called <hi>Pſalmes of degrees,</hi> which it is thought by ſome are ſo called, becauſe there were 15. ſteps or degrees to that part of the Temple, where men were to worſhip the Lord, on which the ſacred Choriſters of divine muſick ſung theſe 15. Pſalms. How ever that were ſo or no, our Temple of praiſe has 15. notable ſteps or ſtairs, on which we may ſtand and ſing our Pſalms of degrees, which have in them contained ſo many <hi>Hallellu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah's</hi> for ſo many remarkable branches of our ſalvation. That we may the better take notice of them, let us gather them together and make them faggots of juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or ſweet-wood, to kindle our fire of thankfulneſſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt branch of this ſalvation, is the ſpeciall providence of God, in making
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111424:6"/>ſuch an union, as ſouldiers, townſ-men, ſea-men, ſtrangers were all united cloſely as one man, to ſtand couragiouſly againſt the common enemy; wheras they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out did hope there would have bin a diviſion within, and that diviſion would have bin the mother and ſure ſeminary of confuſion and ruine. For dividing and deſtroying commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly go together, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.9. or are but a very little while parted aſunder, <hi>A kingdome</hi> (a town) <hi>an houſe divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand, Divide</hi> and <hi>Impera</hi> come from the braines of the old divident, who ſet up a ſchoole of Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick in paradiſe, and taught the unhappy rule of diviſion betwixt God and man. Diviſion commonly puts an enemy into the Imperative mood. But bleſſed be the God of union, who is but one, and made this people of one heart, and one way in this buſineſſe, though a people as likely to fall into bad peeces as any.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond branch, with ſweet berries growing on it, was the Lords care to give food to his people and preſervation of the mils, which in all probability they might have attempted to beat down, or fire at the firſt, as well as they attempted it at the laſt, by raiſing a work hard behind one of them. Yea though they had pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us faſt in 6 weeks together, yet the Lord provided better meat then Quailes, and though we had not <hi>Manna</hi> from heaven, yet we had rain from heaven, which ſtood us in very good ſtead, when our freſh water was cut off. So many Beeves and ſheep were preſerved from thoſe great cattel ſtealers, that meat a good while was cheaper in the ſiege then out of it, and I believe the proud enemy in a great part of the Army, would have licked their lips at our fragments. <hi>David</hi> thinks we have good reaſon to praiſe the Lord with our whole heart, even for giving meat to them that feare him. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 111.1. &amp; 5. verſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third branch of ſaving mercy, was in the firing of the North block-houſe blown up in a part, where the powder-barrels and hand Granado's, ill companions being together, and ſome fire coming to that Aſſembly, it blew up with a terrible blaſt, a part of that ſtrong building, yet for all this Gods power and mercy orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it excellently, the Lord commanding the fire and fury to be within on our ſide and not to the enemies part, that they might have no advantage at all by it. The Lord if he had ſo pleaſed might have made a fearefull rupture by it, and opened a gap for them, which they that were ſo prodigall of mans bloud, would with fury have ſet upon, though it had coſt them a thouſand men. Further when the blaſt in one room had beaten open the window into another, and the flame entered into it, where there were 12. barrels of powder more, and ſome with looſe covers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened, it pleaſed the divine diſpenſer to ſuſpend the flame, and it reverently held and drew back from ſeaſing upon that powder, which in al likelihood might have done far more harm, both to murthering of more men, and diſmounting the ordnance. Nor did the enemy ſcape in this kind, for they had a magazin blown up and their ſtore of Granado's, which they had provided for us. Ours, as it did us ſome hurt, ſo it did them no good at all. Bleſt be the Lord, for ſo ſpeciall a branch of his ſalvation.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111424:7"/>
            <p n="4">4. When their great bullets of 35. lb. weight, both roaſt and raw, hot and cold, came ſo faſt and frequently into the Towne, and all over it, they having a great mark to ſhoot at, and likely to ſpeed where ever they fell; yet though day and night they came into ſtreets, houſes, beds, the Lord ſo charmed and charged them, that but 3 were ſlain by them, a man, a woman, and a child. Heaven found ſtrange means, to conjure theſe bullets into quietnes, and ſtop their force. One quarrel'd with a poudring-tub, another ſtuck in paſte, which was a providing for food, and was choked in dough; another drunk it ſelf our friend in a barrell of wine; another burnt the bed-clothes, and ſpared a woman in the bed, ſo as ſhe ſlept ſtill ſoundly and quietly, having ſo hot a bed-fellow, till ſhe was by neighbours wakened and pulled out from the fiery danger. They aimed at our Churches, when we were met together for the word and prayer, yet never hurt any in the Church, going or returning. But in their quarters and at <hi>York</hi> fame rang another peale, of many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds ſlain in the town, and divers coming to, and going from the Church. We al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe two Univerſities of lies, the one of <hi>Oxford,</hi> the other of <hi>York</hi> their poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and lying licence. We have found thoſe two <hi>Africaes</hi> alwaies bringing forth monſtrous things, and lies of a prime magnitude. We are begun to thinke, that it may almoſt gain the ſtrength of a proverb, that <hi>Yorks</hi> printer, minter and minſter, (when they print or preach of the Parliaments affairs) ſeldom vent ſmall lies. The ſouldiers complain of their minter, for minting too much falſe mony, and for their minſters Sermons, aiming at our cauſe, they ſmell very little of truth or charitable divinity; and their printed Pamphlets are notorious. Pardon this digreſſion and going out of the way to cudgell a liar.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When they were ſo neare, as within reach of Granado's as they truſted, yet we heard but only of 3 or 4 of them, and thoſe were either ſhort or over: where they digged deep into guts of earth, but touched not any man. What would they have done, if the Lord had given theſe hot officers of his anger leave to come into market, Churches, ſtreets, houſes, what terrible marks would they have left of their burning and tearing foot-ſteps.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Our iſſuings out proved moſtly ſuccesfull to us, though with ſmall ſtrength, but alwaies hurtfull, to the coſt and loſſe of the enemy, looſing men, and having ſome worke pulled down by ours, they flying as driven away.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Our horſe were happily preſerved, and ſafely conveyed into <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> when our freſh water &amp; fodder was ſo little, as ſtaying they ſhould have had ſhort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and many of them would have periſht being foodles, and all of them would have bin uſeles, becauſe of the enemies propinquity and nearneſſe. God reſerved them for another place, where they were ſerviceable in a glorious victory.</p>
            <p n="8">8. When the ſtate of the Town was very depreſſed, and earthly hopes were at a low nepe, our men being few, and worne out with day labours and night-watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and fightings from their works, there being not ſufficient for number to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111424:7"/>the works wel, and clothe the wals, if the enemy ſhould approach nearer. In that very nick of neceſſity, God ſent us a competent number of ſouldiers, with that good Commander S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Meldram,</hi> that did exceedingly animate and put freſh ſpirits into our wearied ſouldiers, and very much conduce to our great help.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When on a ſudden, a company of their pickt and reſolute ſpirits, with fury and ſtrength had almoſt got one of our beſt works, the weſt jutty, and were in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner poſſeſſors of it, yet ours ſlew and diſcomfited them, ſo as divers of them were ſlain, ſome 15. and ſome taken priſoners. The reſt fled away with wounds &amp; ſhame, as full of cold fear, as they came full of ſtrong water, of which the ſlain and taken notably ſavoured, having fired their ſpirits into a deſperatenes with the ſpirits of hot waters. In all the time God ſo wrought for us, we held the works we had. And this deſerves a finger to point at it, a tongue to praiſe for it.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Lord pared away from the ſtrength of their numerous Army, by a reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſicknes among them, by the running away of many, and by diverting a part of their forces into <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> that they might be ſomething weaker, and more fit for us to deale with them, though ſtill their numbers did treble ours.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Marvellous was the Lord in the prevention of their firing the Town &amp; ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, which they were mad to doe, and confident would be done, either by their wild-fire, or wild bullets glowing hot (they imitating the fiery darts of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the wicked one) yet the Lord kept them from lighting on combuſtible mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or eaſily fire-catching ſtuffe. They were ſo confident of burning us, that they cauſed country people divers times to ſtand on an hill, &amp; promiſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with great oaths and damning language, they ſhould preſently ſee <hi>Hull</hi> on a light fire, but God ſent no fire to conſume their ſacrifice in token of acceptation. They are ſerved with the <hi>Germane</hi> proverbe, <hi>Deus non audit felium preces,</hi> God hears not cats pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to accept them, that is curſes and execrations, more unwelcome to God then the harſh cries of cats. No, when their Apoſtle M. <hi>Thruſcroſſe</hi> (who no doubt is wel-pleaſed that the croſſe is found in his name) ſpeaks of winning <hi>Hull,</hi> he tels them they muſt faſt and pray, or els never thinke to win it: for, ſaith he, you fight againſt a praying people. He fore-ſaw curſes, that come from a tongue and heart ſet on fire of hell, could never ſet on fire <hi>Hull,</hi> and therefore he gave them more ghoſtly counſell. And they report from <hi>Pomfret,</hi> which I annex, that a man, and they name the man, came from that Town towards <hi>Hull,</hi> big with expectation and hope to ſee it on fire, and when he returned he found his own houſing fired. So wiſely and juſtly doth God meet with men in unjuſt and cruell waies. Beſides firing, they were by the ſame providence prevented of blocking up the river, when on <hi>Lincolnſhires</hi> ſide and <hi>Holderneſſes,</hi> they were begun to make forts, but by ſome of our men landing were driven away, and the fort was razed down.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In compaſſe of ſix weeks, all which time they begirt us with that ſtrait and troubleſome girdle of a ſiege, by our ſallyings out, and all their bullets ſallying in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111424:8"/>among us, not 60. perſons as 'tis thought were ſlain in all of ours, few or none of note, when 'tis certain of theirs above 2000 are periſht by ſword, bullet, ſickneſſe and abundance of them fairly tryed their heels and deſerted them. Some of their Commanders of note, Lieutenant-Col. <hi>Levinſton,</hi> Serj. maj. <hi>Boyard,</hi> Cap. <hi>Knight,</hi> and many others, which they conceale from us in the dark book of ſecrecy, went to their laſt bed in the dark chambers of death before <hi>Hull.</hi> Divers of their Captains that had compleat companies went back to <hi>York</hi> with ragged remains of ſome 9 or 6 of thoſe they carried out thence, and many in great numbers, grievouſly wounded to make up their black triumph ſome went with them, and after them others, to adorne their glorious carriages.</p>
            <p n="13">13. It was a notable favour of heaven, that ſuch a reſolute and couragious ſpirit was raiſed in ours, as that they went out, and ſet upon the enemy, the wedneſday 7 night before, being <hi>Oct.</hi> 4. and beat them out of two of their works, ſlew and took ſome, and brought in many of their muskets, which they running away left. One of thoſe works they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d newly raiſed behind our wind-mil, which was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hopefull one for them, and was likely to be very damagefull to us, had it bin let alone but that night. But God was in ſome ſort viſible that day, giving ours pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to beat thoſe wild and furious cocks on and off their own dung-hill. And that Wedneſday was a fairly ominous preface to the next Wedneſday, which was vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous to us in big mercies.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Further, when this day of bleſſings, <hi>Oct.</hi> 11. the day wheron the ſiege was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, was well gone on for us, the other gathering much freſh force, came on for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midably againſt ours, inſomuch as our ſouldiers are body and ſoul for a retreat, and ſhamefull retire. See now how hoavenly providence comes in to ſuccour. Ours were baſely timid, and prophecied dangerous things to themſelves, from the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies freſh and full appearance, where one ſudden cloud of feare, was likely to be the blacke mantle or curtain, to hide the light of a very hopefull day. Some good ſpirits of Captains and ſouldiers were as much tormented with ſhame, to ſee ſo ſick a fit upon our armie, as the retreaters were tormented with feare; wherupon ſome Commanders, and by-ſtanding ſpectators did earneſtly beg and beſeech they would turn again and face the enemy, and ſome of the horſe couragiouſly leading the way, and giving a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſh on-ſet, it animated the foot, where the <hi>Spirit of the Lord</hi> ſet up a Standard in their ſpirits, and they fell on bravely, and out of <hi>weaknes</hi> were made <hi>ſtrong, Heb.</hi> 11.34. and turned the enemy into ſmoake, which fled before them as driven by the wind, ſhewing many backs, but few faces againſt ours, in which backs they ſee faire printed the adverſaries defeat, and their own victory. God ſo bleſſes this new aſſault, that they take from them their great guns, 9. of them, ſome greater, ſome leſſe, beats them from their ſtrong &amp; great works with very little and ſmall loſſe of ours, in which great pecces and works many of them truſted, more then in the great God. Our Cap. <hi>Rainsborow</hi> by a miſtake was taken, but for him we had many of theirs fell priſoners into our hands.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111424:8"/>
            <p>This 11. of <hi>Oct.</hi> was a great and glorious day, that ſuch multitudes of men out of many and ſtrong works, from many and great guns ſhould be beaten and driven away by them, that came to aſſault them in the open field, is a rare example of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to the Parlia. battels, and is as notable a peece of pure military valour, as has faln out ſince the beginning of theſe wars. The ſouldiers, that went home by wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and bleeding croſſe, doe cry out of our ſtratagem to retreat on purpoſe, and then with renewed ſtrength to come and ruine them. Indeed it was a brave ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem and a rare plot, but it was Gods ſtratagem and a plot of providence, which we never contrived nor thought on, till his waking thoughts brought it about. How comfortably did the whole Towne almoſt look over the walles that whole day, and ſee this ſalvation of God?</p>
            <p n="15">15. Laſtly, being thus breakfaſted on wedneſday, that night they ſup with fears and curſes, and haſty purpoſes of being gone from us. The Lord on a ſudden ſweeps them away, they ſteale away the remaining Ordnance in the night. A <hi>ſpirit of fear</hi> lends them wings to fly, they go away with ſhame, loſſe and ſtinging conſciences: So that the ſiege is raiſed, w<hi rend="sup">h</hi> we expected not; the enemy is gone ſuddenly, we lookt not for it. Many of them left their muskets and other weapons in the works, and though it was a very ſore day of rain, yet away they muſt, they dare not ſtay for fair weather. Preſently our ſtate is marvellouſly changed, we heare not of their guns, we receive no more ridings of their fiery bullets, we are deliver'd and yet doubt whether we do but dream of it. How are our fears and foes ſuddenly vaniſht, &amp; we quickly reſtored to walking on freſh ground, breathing in freſh air, having enough of freſh water, &amp; many comforts our enemies had ſtraitned us in? They gave out they raiſed the ſiege, becauſe of the wet weather, &amp; I believe it; for they had ſome caſe-ſhot among them, with ſtore of other bullets; which made that a wet day, though it was very fair, in that it could not but rain good ſtore of bad bloud. God has overcome us and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflown us in our deſires: we looked but for a little, and the ſea of mercy has broke out and drowned us with a deluge and <hi>cataclyſme</hi> of bleſſings.</p>
            <p>The Country mourns, yet God made us to laugh. They are impoveriſhed every way in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and goods and men: their beſt tables, trees, timber are taken and laid in the ditches by the enemy, to help the conveyance of carriages &amp; ordnance from work to work Only their haſty and Eagle-flighted fear has done ſome this kindnes not intended, that they have filled the barns with corn, and in an unkind kindnes (as having no time to threſh it out, to ſell it, or carry it away) have left it for the owners, who finde it, at their repoſſeſſion, gathered to their hands by ſervants whom they never ſet on worke. Nor is this all, God when in his mercy he flows, he overflowes. On the ſame 11<hi rend="sup">h</hi> of <hi>Oct.</hi> he gives us a glorious victory in <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> as free, fair and full as the moſt have bin got fince the unhappy hatching of theſe warrs, ſo as that day hath given them an aſtoniſhing blow, that they have ſtaggered ever ſince, &amp; know not on what ground to tread, God following them with ſoul-ſtupifying terrours. Theſe are the full branches of the Lords ſaving providence, the firſt fruits of our expected harveſt in this miſerable country of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> where ſome 80 not of the meaneſt Gentry have proved drunke with the Queens cup, full of <hi>Roman</hi> intoxicating ſpice, and have made a mad market-venture of their names, families, eſtates, bodies, ſouls, only to preſerve the Papiſts reliques, and the Prelates micers and damaske caſſocks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us. Now theſe furious <hi>Salamanders</hi> and fanſie-frantick ſpirits, begin to ſee, their buſie acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may come to end in miſerable paſſion, becauſe they doted on their lady <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp; have forſaken the Lord Ieſus in his cauſe. Take we but theſe 15. acts of grace, put we them together as ſo many letters, &amp; ſee if they do not evidently compoſe theſe a words, <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> which ran in &amp; thorow the whole action, &amp; therfore all tongues ſhould ſould <hi>the divine Praiſe.</hi> Eſpecially ô <hi>Hull</hi> thou haſt by this day faln into great debt to God, who has taken away thine Alaſtors and Furies
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111424:9"/>from thee. Let thy <hi>Motto</hi> be that of the L. <hi>Boyls</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as I have heard, <hi>Gods Providence is mine Inheritance.</hi> Bleſſe God from the ground of thy heart, that though they were proudly &amp; audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſing of thy houſes, ſtreets, &amp; great mens eſtates, thus &amp; thus, this to, that commander, that to this officer, &amp; gladding themſelves with the rich ſpoils of their preſently to be caught prey, yet there is not one of the to be found in thy town or houſes as poſſeſſors, but only as priſoners. What a mercy is it, that thou art not filled with that luſtfull and letcherous vermin, with that ſpawn of cruelty, that to their power would deſtroy ſouls as wel as bodies. Let a Miniſter of ours of good credit witnes their vertues, who being late their priſoner at <hi>Cottingham,</hi> was carried into a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where an Officer of theirs lay in bed with 2 whors at once, and there was another bed at feet, where another lay with another whore.
<note n="*" place="margin">This vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous provoſt Marſhall ſhewed the whares to him, &amp; told him he did this to vex the round heads, not caring at all, or remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that it vexes God more.</note> Surely <hi>Rome</hi> has need to ſend out a new Bull, for the comfort and pardon of theſe beaſts. Without doubt this is the only way to maintain <hi>the Liberty of the Subject,</hi> &amp; the <hi>known Laws of the Land,</hi> &amp; theſe men go the direct way to ſet up the <hi>Proteſtant Religior.</hi> It were well they had grace to purge their hearts, as well as theſe unholy waies to purge their reins But God hath given them over <hi>to act all wickednes with greedines and impudency,</hi> ſo far as they have a <hi>famous whore,</hi> a <hi>minion</hi> to one of their. <hi>Lords,</hi> who goes openly among them with her piſtols, &amp; bears the name of one that has a troop. Al theſe vertues <hi>Catholick</hi> &amp; <hi>Cardinal</hi> ſhould have bin acted in thy ſtreets &amp; houſes ô <hi>Hull,</hi> to make thee as miſerable a ſeene as unhappy <hi>York.</hi> Either ſtudy <hi>Hallelujabs</hi> &amp; holines al thy daies, &amp; ſet forward ſome new act of reformation for thy men &amp; manners, to the honour of God, or els thou art the unhappieſt Town, that this day ſtands upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground. Set up a royall pillar in the market-place, &amp; in golden letters engrave this delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: or ſet up an holy ſtatue of heavenly purpoſes in your hearts, to be a more holy Town, leſſe proud, luxurious, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or els by this I teſtifie to all the land, God has ſome other ſcourge for thee, to which he will reſerve thee, who has hither to preſerved thee. O that you were wiſe, that as God has bin Al for you, ſo you would be ſomthing more then heretofore for him, or els this great mercy will undo you. Be perſwaded to ſing the mercies of this day, ſo long as you have a day. Call it not the ſouldiers, nor the ſeamans work, but only the Lords, who only doth wondrous things. When God is found ſo much a bleſſed Dative,
<note place="margin">Calv. in opuſc. in praefat. ad Bald. con.</note> take heed thou be not a curſed and unjuſt Ablative, as <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> ſaith, one <hi>Baldwin</hi> was named for lurching things from his fellow-ſtudents.</p>
            <p>By this I have endeavoured to lay out in plain colours this large ſalvation, that the land may know it, and when they heare of extraordinary mercies, they may name <hi>Londons</hi> mercies, <hi>Gloceſters</hi> deliverance, and <hi>Hills</hi> ſalvation. By this, as a performance of my vows in part, I publiſh the goodnes of God to me and thoſe with me, that under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Divine Feathers</hi> were preſerved in the circumvallation of Atheiſticall and cruell ſpirits. And by this let me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh all the Lords ſcattered ones,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Pet. 2.4.</note> who have found the ſalutary and ſaving breathings and blaſts of the celeſtial <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrus</hi> of ſpecial providence, to fal down &amp; ſay with <hi>Heze. The living, the living, he ſhall praiſe thee,</hi> as I do this day: the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the children ſhal make known thy truth <hi>The Lord was ready to ſave me: ther fore we will ſing our ſongs to the ſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged inſtruments all the daies of our life, Iſa</hi> 38 19, 10 Henceforth let <hi>Cavendiſh</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the ſigns in <hi>Nottinghamſhire,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with his Armes and Motto, <hi>Cavendo Tutus.</hi> This will be as good a Monitor for ſetting upon <hi>Hull,</hi> as for them that enter a Tavern or Ale houſe: &amp; as it is his own, let him betime draw practicall Rules from it. For his ſhattered and bullet-batter'd Army, let them flie to their old Letany, <hi>From Hell, Hull, Halifax deliver us,</hi> and leave out their <hi>God damne me,</hi> for their damnation in hell will be worſe then their confuſion at <hi>Hull.</hi> Nor need they wiſh it, and ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire it; for S <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, the damnation of ſuch ſleeps not, and if it did ſleep, I am ſure this ſect of <hi>God damniſts</hi> are likely to wake it, that it ſhall have but a ſhort ſleep. I conclude with a Text for thee O <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon this thy deliverance with <hi>Ezra's</hi> words, and with ſutable works. <hi>Seeing thou our God hast given us ſuch a deliverance as this,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 9.13, 14.</note> ſhould we again break thy commandements, and ioyn in league with the people of theſe abominations? Wouldſt thou not be angry with us, till thou hadſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant, nor eſcaping?</hi> Admiration was the mother of Philoſophy, let it be the mother of your Divinity, in this thing to admire the Lords wonderfull mercy, wiſdome and power, that did ſo act and worke for an handfull of his people, whom he might have thrown out of the way, and there could no Iudge or Iury have found him guilty of any thing for it, but iuſtice and righteouſneſſe in the action. Wherefore ſeaſon all your hearts with ſenſe of unworthineſſe on our part, and ample apprehenſions of goodnes on his part, that the flame within and without, may alwaies keep you in heat with this fire, burning you up with admiration of ſpirit, and exaltation of God, both in language and life, till you be ready to live and die in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> temper, Pſ 72, 18.19. <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, the God of Iſrael, who only doth wondroue things. And bleſſed be his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name for ever, and let the whole earth be filled with his glory. Amen and Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
